Guide to the Lucien Carr Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Lucien Carr Papers,
1951-1975.
Carr, Lucien, 1925-2005.
0.5 linear ft. (1 document box and 3 oversize folders).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0201
4078588
A founding member of the Beat Generation, Carr was a friend of Allen Ginsberg, Jack Kerouac, and other beat writers, and attended Columbia University in 1944. The Lucien Carr Papers contain correspondence with prominent Beat writers Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac, as well as some clippings and ephemera.
Biographical Note
Lucien Carr was born in New York City in 1925, but spent most of his childhood in St. Louis, Missouri. It was in St. Louis that he first met Washington University instructor David Kammerer and Kammerer's childhood friend William S. Burroughs.
After graduating from Andover Academy, Carr briefly enrolled in Bowdoin College, but soon transferred to the University of Chicago, where he stayed for two semesters until an apparent suicide attempt caused him to be briefly institutionalized. His mother, living in New York at the time, convinced Carr to transfer to Columbia University. At Columbia, Carr, a brilliant student, befriended his Columbia dormmate Allen Ginsberg and recent graduate, Jack Kerouac. He introduced Ginsberg and Kerouac to one another and to William Burroughs, who, along with Kammerer, had moved to New York in Carr's wake. The intelligent and charismatic Carr quickly became the ringleader of the group of friends--introducing them to the sensualist poetry of Rimbaud and encouraging their exploration of Greenwich Village clubs.
This period of Carr's life ended abruptly when, after a night of drinking, Kammerer made increasingly persistent and aggressive sexual advances on Carr in Riverside Park. The situation became violent and resulted in Carr stabbing and killing Kammerer. He was convicted of manslaughter and served two years in prison for the crime.
Though Carr was instrumental in the bringing together the key players who would form the core of the Beat Generation, he later remained on the periphery of the movement. He valued his privacy, and asked that his name not be mentioned in press relating to the beats and even requesting that Allen Ginsberg remove his name from the dedication of "Howl." Though he moved out of the spotlight, he remained close with his college friends, supporting Kerouac and Ginsberg throughout their careers, including briefly allowing Kerouac to live with him and his wife while Kerouac worked on the manuscript for On the Road.
He married Francesca (Cessa) van Hartz and took a job at United Press International where he worked as an editor for the entirety of his 47-year career in the news business. He and Francesca had three children--Simon, Ethan, and the writer Caleb Carr--before they divorced.
Carr died of complications of bone cancer in 2005.
Scope and Content
The Lucien Carr papers contain Carr's correspondence, primarily with Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac, as well as clippings, book reviews, and articles relating to Ginsberg, Kerouac, Burroughs, and other Beat Generation figures.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1956-1975
Series II: Printed Material and Ephemera, 1951-1973
Subjects
Columbia University--Students.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; Carr, Lucien, 1925-2005.; Cru, Henri.; Poets, American--20th century.; American literature--20th century.; Beat Generation.; Bohemianism.; American poetry--20th century.; Manuscripts.; Photoprints.
Acquisition
1977 M-77 Purchase
- Series I: Correspondence, 1956-1973
  The correspondence series contains letters, telegrams, and postcards sent to Carr from his friends Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac. Some of these letters include fragments of works in progress, such as the Ginsberg letter that includes an early draft of the first section of "Howl: For Carl Solomon." Many of Kerouac's letters take the form of poems.
  - Cru, Henri to Jack Kerouac
    - [1957] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [1957] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ginsberg, Allen to Lucien Carr
    - January 16, 1956 (includes early draft of "Howl" with author's corrections) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - April 4, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - October, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - December 11, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - May 30, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - January 26, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - April 6, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - April 20, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - January 17, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - March 28, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - January 28, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - February 14, 1966 (Box 14-E-7)
    - July 3, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - October 1, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - July 17, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - July 19, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - August 17, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - November 4, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - March 22, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - October 13, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - October 16, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - November 21, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - July 27, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - August, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - August 19, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - September 16, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - March 8, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - March 17, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - March 27, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - May 24, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - June 2, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - June 12, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - June 24, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - August 10, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - November 10, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Kerouac, Jack to Lucien Carr
    - Undated (includes a pencil sketch of a woman's head) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - February 24, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - February 28, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - March 12, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - October 22, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - November 20, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - December 14, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - January 16, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - February 18, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - August 14, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - May 23, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - October 12, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - January 19, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - May 17, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - October 31, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - December 27, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - January 6, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - March 15, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - May 28, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - June 7, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - August 11, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - June 2, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Kerouac, Jack to Francesca Carr
    - October 22, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Series II: Printed Material and Ephemera, 1951-1973
  The printed Material and Ephemera series is comprised of clippings, articles, publications, and book reviews relating to members of the Beat Generation and their work. Also included are three small photographs, two of Allen Ginsberg and one of William Burroughs, and a typed copy of the Buddhist text The Diamond Sutra that was owned by Jack Kerouac.
  - Clippings regarding Ginsberg and Burroughs, 1957, 1959 and undated (Box 14-E-7)
  - Clippings regarding Kerouac, 1957-1959 (mostly book reviews) (Box 14-E-7)
  - "Rimbaud" published poem by Jack Kerouac, 1960 (2 copies- 1 inscribed to Lafcadio [Orlovsky]) (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Typed copy of The Diamond Sutra (typed, owned and annotated by Jack Kerouac) (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Photographs
    - Ginsberg in San Francisco, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Burroughs in Colombia, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - "The Beat Generation and the Continuing Revolution" by John Tytell, 1973 published in The American Scholar (Box 1, Folder 70)